A Guide to the Confederate Pension Records, 1884-1978
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Confederate Pension Records, 1884-1978
The Library of Virginia
44105
46.75 cubic feet (127 boxes and 35 volumes)
Virginia. Dept. of Accounts
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records came in several accessions and were combined into one body of records under Acc. 44105. Included are the following accessions: 25311, 26270, 26418, 26835, 28020, 28021, 28023, 28306, & 29468.
Historical Information
The Virginia General Assembly passed Confederate pension acts in 1888, 1900, and 1902, and a series of supplementary acts between 1903 and 1934. The act of 1888 provided pensions to Confederate soldiers, sailors, and marines disabled in action and to the widows of those killed in action. Subsequent acts broadened the coverage to include all veterans, their widows and their unmarried or widowed daughters. The act required that applicants be residents of Virginia. Later legislation included veterans or their survivors residing in the District of Columbia as well. An act of the Assembly passed in 1924 provided a pension of twenty-five dollars to any person who accompanied a Confederate soldier in services as a body-servant or who was detailed as a guard, cook, hostler or teamster, etc. Additional subsequent acts increased pension payments and categorized pensioners into several classes based on their disability.
On 15 March 1902, the General Assembly passed an act to appropriate certain sums of money from the public treasury in aid of Confederate memorial associations having in charge cemeteries containing the graves of Confederate soldiers. This act instructed the auditor of public accounts to draw an annual warrant from the treasurer in favor of the treasurers of various memorial associations. Subsequent acts have been passed through the present time for appropriating funds for the care and upkeep of Confederate cemeteries and graves.
An act providing for the funeral expenses of Confederate soldiers or widows enrolled on the pension roll was passed by the General Assembly on 11 March 1908. This act provided twenty-five dollars for funeral expenses of any Confederate pensioner or any widow on the pension roll of the state of Virginia. The act required a certificate of the clerk of the circuit court regarding the death of the pensioner. The auditor of public accounts was then responsible for issuing a warrant for funeral expenses.
On 1 March 1928 the Office of the Comptroller in the Department of Accounts assumed the functions of the Auditor of Public Accounts with regard to Confederate pensions.
Scope and Content
The Confederate Pension Records consist of 118 boxes and 35 volumes and are arranged in eight series. Series have been designated for Applications, Card Files, Certificates, Confederate Memorial Association, Correspondence, Funeral Expenses, Miscellaneous, and Volumes. This collection documents pension payments to Confederate veterans, widows, daughters, and servants. These records should not be confused with The Library of Virginia's Confederate Pension Rolls which should be searched before any examination of the Confederate Pension Records (Click Here to Search Pensions). The Confederate Pension Records differ from the Confederate Pension Rolls in that they serve as the administrative and financial documentation for the pension rolls. Even though there are pension applications for daughters of Confederate veterans within the Confederate Pension Records, the Confederate Pension Rolls are the best source for these types of records. It is these applications that provide the most extensive information on the Confederate pensioners. The strength of the Confederate Pension Records is that they provide information on maiden daughters or widowed daughters of Confederate veterans who received a pension from the state of Virginia. The Confederate Pension Rolls do not provide information on Confederate daughters who received pensions. In addition, the Confederate Pension Records document pension payments forty years beyond the documentation in the Confederate Pension Rolls.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Applications, 1913-1975 (bulk 1913-1929, 1967-1975)
Subseries A: Daughters Enrolled, 1967-1977
Subseries B: Rerating Applications, 1913-1929
Series II: Card Files, 1930-1975
Subseries A: Payroll Cards, 1930-1977
Sub Subseries 1: Daughters, 1942-1977
Sub Subseries 2: Soldiers, Widows, and Servants, 1930-1966
Sub Subseries 3: Widows, 1939-1970
Subseries B: United Daughters of the Confederacy Convention Registration Cards, n.d.
Series III: Certificates, 1908-1960 (bulk 1925-1958)
Subseries A: Allowed Certificates, 1908-1960 (bulk 1925-1958)
Sub Subseries 1: Servants, 1927-1950 (bulk 1927-1928)
Sub Subseries 2: Soldiers, 1925-1950 (bulk 1925-1928)
Sub Subseries 3: Widows, 1927-1974 (bulk 1927-1928, 1949-1958)
Subseries B: Disallowed Certificates, 1908-1929 (bulk 1916-1929)
Series IV: Confederate Memorial Association, 1946-1972
Series V: Correspondence, 1921-1977 (bulk, 1921-1925, 1960-1972)
Subseries A: Confederate Pension Administrator, 1963-1972
Subseries B: Deceased Daughters, 1965-1977
Subseries C: Deceased Widows, 1960-1973
Subseries D: Incoming Correspondence, 1923-1925
Subseries E: Pension Clerk's Correspondence, 1921-1924
Series VI: Funeral Expenses, 1909-1967 (bulk 1918-1929)
Subseries A: Allowed Claims, 1926-1967 (bulk 1926-1929)
Subseries B: Disallowed Claims, 1909, 1918-1930 (bulk 1918-1929)
Series VII: Miscellaneous, 1884-1973
Series VIII: Volumes, 1933-1978
Subseries A: Daughter Pensions, 1924-1958
Subseries B: Veteran and Widow Pensions, 1933-1958
Subseries C: Registers, 1933-1947
Subseries D: Warrant Registers, 1961-1978
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also Confederate Pension Rolls (Searchable from Virginia Memory on the Library of Virginia website)
Separated Material
Oversized documents separated to Box 118.
Contents List
- Series I: Applications, 1913-1975., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 1-4.)
  The Applications series is housed in four archival boxes and is arranged in two subseries. Subseries have been designated for Daughters Enrolled and Rerating Applications. This series documents applications from both Civil War veterans and daughters of veterans for pensions or changes to pensions. Please note that the Rerating Applications subseries is incomplete.
  Arranged into two subseries.
  - Subseries A: Daughters Enrolled, 1967-1977., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 1-2.)
    The Daughters Enrolled subseries is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged in chronological order. This subseries contains applications for Confederate pensions to be filed with the United Daughters of the Confederacy. The applications provide the following information: the name of the widowed daughter, the name of the Confederate veteran, his regiment, date of birth, age, & address. In addition, the application asks several questions as to whether or not their father or mother received a Confederate pension from Virginia, whether or not they own their own home, whether or not they own property, and whether or not they own stocks or bonds. The applications often include a certificate from the Virginia State Library documenting the name of the veteran, his rank, unit, captain, date & place enlisted, & remarks. The applications sometimes include correspondence from the applicant, Nancy W. Stoll who served as Confederate Pension Administrator, and others.
    Arranged in chronological order.
    - 1967-1968
      - A-G (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - H-L (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - M-Z (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1968-1969
      - A-G (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - H-L (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - M-W (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1969-1970
      - A-G (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - H-M (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - N-W (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B: Rerating Applications, 1905-1929., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 2-4.)
    The Rerating Applications subseries is housed in three archival boxes and is arranged by allowed applications and disallowed applications. The applications are further arranged alphabetically by locality with cities at the rear of the subseries. This subseries contains applications from Confederate pensioners to be rerated and classed as totally disabled. The applications provide the following information: name, age, address, occupation, income, disability, physician, etc. In addition, the application includes a certificate of physician, a certificate of the commissioner of the revenue, a certificate of the pension board, and a certificate of a judge. The application often also includes copies of correspondence from the pension clerk or pensioner. Note that there are only three localities present for allowed rerating applications. The location of the missing localities is unknown.
    Arranged by allowed or disallowed applications, then alphabetically by locality.
    - Allowed
      - Campbell County, 1905-1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Caroline County, 1906-1919 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Pulaski County, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Disallowed
      - Accomack-Augusta, 1917-1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Bedford-Brunswick, 1916-1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Buchanan-Charlotte, 1916-1926 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Chesterfield-Essex, 1917-1925 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Fairfax-Greensville, 1917-1928 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Highland-Lynchburg, 1917-1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Mathews-Nelson, 1916-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Nottoway-Powhatan, 1917-1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Prince Edward-Rockingham, 1920-1928 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Russell-Scott, 1918-1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Shenandoah-Tazewell, 1916-1929 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Wayne-Wythe, 1915-1927 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Buena Vista-Winchester, 1917-1926 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II: Card Files, 1930-1977., Extent: 22 boxes. (Box 5-26.)
  The Card Files series is housed in twenty-two archival boxes and is arranged in two series. Subseries have been designated for Payroll Cards and United Daughters of the Confederacy Registration Cards. The Payroll Cards are the more useful and important subseries. The Card Files series provides a good ready reference source of Confederate pensioners. In addition, the Card Files can be used to determine a pensioner's date of death. These cards provide similar information including name, roll number, locality, veteran's name, veteran's unit, amount of annual pension, date approved, date died, date death reported, remarks, and amount paid each quarter. Some of the cards are stamped "dead" or "dropped" from pension roll. Little is known of the United Daughters of the Confederacy Convention Registration Cards, but they do contain information on veterans and widows of veterans who attended one of the UDC conventions in Richmond.
  - Subseries A: Payroll Cards, 1930-1977, Extent: 21 boxes. (Box 5-25.)
    The Payroll Cards subseries is housed in twenty-one archival boxes and is arranged in three sub subseries. Sub subseries have been designated for Daughters; Soldiers, Widows, and Servants; and Widows. The Soldiers, Widows, and Servants sub subseries documents the earliest payroll cards date from 1930 and include veterans, widows of veterans, and slaves who received pensions from the state of Virginia.
    Arranged in three sub subseries.
    - Sub Subseries 1: Daughters, 1942-1966, 6 boxes. (Box 5-10)
      The Daughters Sub subseries is housed in nine archival boxes and is arranged both alphabetically and chronologically. This sub subseries documents pension payments to maiden or widowed daughters and sisters of Confederate veterans. Alphabetically arranged files are first arranged chronologically in three chronological subdivisions: 1942-1951, 1951-1960, and 1957-1966. These chronological subdivisions are based on the printed years on the cards used to track pension payments for each quarter. Within these chronological subdivisions, the daughter payrolls are arranged alphabetically by pensioner. The other arrangement in this sub subseries represents daughters who died between 1961 and 1977. These cards are arranged chronologically by the year of the pensioner's death, then alphabetically by pensioner.
      Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by pensioner.
      - Alphabetical
        - 1942-1951
          - A-I (Box 5)
          - J-T (Box 6)
          - U-Z (Box 7)
        - 1951-1960
          - A-Mi (Box 8)
          - Mo-Y (Box 9)
        - 1957-1966 (Box 10)
      - Chronological
        - 1961-1967 (Box 11)
        - 1967-1975 (Box 12)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 13)
    - Sub Subseries 2: Soldiers, Widows, and Servants, 1930-1966, 10 boxes. (Box 14-23)
      The Soldiers, Widows, and Servants Sub subseries is housed in ten archival boxes and is arranged both alphabetically and chronologically. This sub subseries documents pension payments to Confederate veterans, widows of veterans, and slaves who contributed to the war effort in some manner. This sub subseries is arranged chronologically in two chronological subdivisions: 1930-1938 and 1939-1966. These chronological subdivisions are based on the printed years on the cards used to track pension payments for each quarter. Within these chronological subdivisions, the payrolls are arranged alphabetically by locality, then alphabetically by pensioner. Note that widow payroll cards can also be found in sub subseries 3.
      Arranged both alphabetically and chronologically (see above).
      - 1930-1938
        - Accomack-Caroline (Box 14)
        - Carroll-Giles (Box 15)
        - Gloucester-Madison (Box 16)
        - Mathews-Rappahannock (Box 17)
        - Richmond-Wise (Box 18)
        - Wythe-Radford (Box 19)
        - Richmond-Washington, D.C. (Box 20)
      - 1939-1966
        - Albemarle-King William (Box 21)
        - Lancaster-Sussex (Box 22)
        - Tazewell-Washington, D.C. (Box 23)
    - Sub Subseries 3: Widows, 1939-1970, 2 boxes. (Box 24-25)
      The Widows Sub subseries is housed in two archival boxes and is arranged both alphabetically and chronologically. This sub subseries documents pension payments to widows of Confederate veterans. Alphabetically arranged files are arranged by locality, then by pensioner. The other arrangement in this sub subseries represents widows who died between 1961 and 1970. These cards are arranged chronologically by the year of the pensioner's death, then alphabetically by pensioner. Note that widow payroll cards can also be found in sub subseries 2.
      - Chronological
        - 1961-1970 (Box 24)
      - Locality, 1939-1948 (Box 25)
  - Subseries B: United Daughters of the Confederacy Convention Registration Cards, n.d., Extent: 1 boxes. (Box 26.)
    The United Daughters of the Confederacy Convention Registration Cards are arranged alphabetically by state, then alphabetically by attendee. This subseries documents the attendance to an unidentified UDC convention held in Richmond, Virginia. The cards provide the following information: name of veteran, wife, widow, attendant, or delegate, address, wartime command, present rank, name of attendant, and lodging which the person was assigned to. The card file includes separate tabs for hotel registrants and visitors to the convention. It appears the main purpose of these cards was to manage lodging for convention attendees. The majority of the attendees appear to have been assigned lodging at the Soldier's Home and various UDC camps.
    Arranged by state, then alphabetically by attendee.
- Series III: Certificates, 1908-1974., Extent: 39 boxes. (Box 27-66.)
  The Certificates series is housed in thirty-nine archival boxes and is arranged in two series. Series have been designated for Allowed and Disallowed certificates. These pension certificates were completed by the pensioner and sent to the Auditor of Public Accounts for payment of their pension. This series represents the largest in the collection. Although the certificates do not contain as much information as the Applications, they are useful since they contain the age of the pensioner.
  - Subseries A: Allowed, 1925-1974., Extent: 38 boxes. (Box 27-65.)
    The Allowed Certificates subseries is housed in thirty-eight and is arranged in three sub-subseries. Sub-subseries have been designated for Servants, Soldiers, and Widows. This is the larger of the two subseries.
    - Sub Subseries 1: Servants, 1927-1951, 1 box. (Box 27)
      The Servant's Certificates sub subseries is housed in one archival box and is arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by locality and pensioner. Servant pension certificates were provided in the act of the General Assembly of 1924 which was amended in 1926. Servant pension certificates were provided for any person who accompanied a Confederate soldier in service, performed guard duty for the Confederacy, served as cook, hostler or teamster, worked on Confederate breastworks, buried Confederate dead, worked in the railroad or blacksmith shops, or who worked in the Confederate hospitals. The certificates provide the name of the servant, age, locality, and a signed affidavit by the pensioner before a notary public. The pensioner certified that he was a resident of the state of Virginia and that they do not hold a state, national, or city office which pays a salary of more than $400 per annum. These certificates sometimes include correspondence from the pensioner to the Pension Department regarding a change of address. Also included is correspondence from John H. Johnson, Pension Clerk, Auditor of Public Accounts, regarding pension checks.
      Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by locality and pensioner.
      - 1927
        - Albemarle-Cumberland (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Dinwiddie-Mecklenburg (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Montgomery-Wythe (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Danville-Staunton (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - 1928
        - Albemarle-Cumberland (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - Dinwiddie-Montgomery (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - Nansemond-Wythe (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - Danville-Staunton (Box 27, Folder 8)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Sub Subseries 2: Soldiers, 1925-1958, 16 boxes. (Box 28-44)
      The Soldier's Certificates sub subseries is housed in sixteen archival boxes and is arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by locality and pensioner. These certificates contain a name, age, locality, signature, witness, and date. The certificates also include the date filed in the Auditor's Office and the amounts & date of each quarterly paid warrant. Each certificate contains an affidavit signed by the pensioner and a witness avowing that they are the person named in the original application with disabilities filed in the office of the clerk of the court for aid as a soldier, sailor, or marine of Virginia in the service of the state or Confederate States of America. The veteran also certified that he is a resident of Virginia and that he does not hold a state, national, or city office which pays a salary of more that $300 per annum (this increased to $400 per annum in 1927). The certificates sometimes include change of address/notification of death cards, applications, and correspondence. The correspondence was sent to John H. Johnson, Pension Clerk, from pensioners and others regarding address changes and the death of pensioners. Noteworthy are the certificates of John Salling, Virginia's last surviving Confederate veteran who died in 1959.
      - 1925
        - Accomack County (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Albemarle County (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Alleghany County (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Amelia County (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Amherst County (Box 28, Folder 5)
        - Appomattox County (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Arlington County (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - Augusta County (Box 28, Folder 8)
        - Bath County (Box 28, Folder 9)
        - Bedford County (Box 28, Folder 10)
        - Bland County (Box 28, Folder 11)
        - Botetourt County (Box 28, Folder 12)
        - Brunswick County (Box 28, Folder 13)
        - Buchanan County (Box 28, Folder 14)
        - Buckingham County (Box 28, Folder 15)
        - Campbell County (Box 28, Folder 16)
        - Caroline County (Box 28, Folder 17)
        - Carroll County (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Charles City County (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Charlotte County (Box 29, Folder 3)
        - Chesterfield County (Box 29, Folder 4)
        - Clarke County (Box 29, Folder 5)
        - Craig County (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Culpeper County (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - Cumberland County (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - Dickenson County (Box 29, Folder 9)
        - Dinwiddie County (Box 29, Folder 10)
        - Elizabeth City County (Box 29, Folder 11)
        - Essex County (Box 29, Folder 12)
        - Fairfax County (Box 29, Folder 13)
        - Fauquier County (Box 29, Folder 14)
        - Floyd County (Box 29, Folder 15)
        - Fluvanna County (Box 29, Folder 16)
        - Franklin County (Box 29, Folder 17)
        - Frederick County (Box 29, Folder 18)
        - Giles County (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - Gloucester County (Box 30, Folder 2)
        - Goochland County (Box 30, Folder 3)
        - Grayson County (Box 30, Folder 4)
        - Greene County (Box 30, Folder 5)
        - Greensville County (Box 30, Folder 6)
        - Halifax County (Box 30, Folder 7)
        - Hanover County (Box 30, Folder 8)
        - Henrico County (Box 30, Folder 9)
        - Henry County (Box 30, Folder 10)
        - Highland County (Box 30, Folder 11)
        - Isle of Wight County (Box 30, Folder 12)
        - James City County (Box 30, Folder 13)
        - King & Queen County (Box 30, Folder 14)
        - King George County (Box 30, Folder 15)
        - King William County (Box 30, Folder 16)
        - Lancaster County (Box 30, Folder 17)
        - Lee County (Box 30, Folder 18)
        - Loudoun County (Box 30, Folder 19)
        - Louisa County (Box 30, Folder 20)
        - Lunenburg County (Box 30, Folder 21)
        - Madison County (Box 30, Folder 22)
        - Mathews County (Box 30, Folder 23)
        - Mecklenburg County (Box 30, Folder 24)
        - Middlesex County (Box 30, Folder 25)
        - Montgomery County (Box 31, Folder 1)
        - Nansemond County (Box 31, Folder 2)
        - Nelson County (Box 31, Folder 3)
        - New Kent County (Box 31, Folder 4)
        - Norfolk County (Box 31, Folder 5)
        - Northampton County (Box 31, Folder 6)
        - Northumberland County (Box 31, Folder 7)
        - Nottoway County (Box 31, Folder 8)
        - Orange County (Box 31, Folder 9)
        - Page County (Box 31, Folder 10)
        - Patrick County (Box 31, Folder 11)
        - Pittsylvania County (Box 31, Folder 12)
        - Powhatan County (Box 31, Folder 13)
        - Prince Edward County (Box 31, Folder 14)
        - Prince George County (Box 31, Folder 15)
        - Prince William County (Box 31, Folder 16)
        - Princess Anne County (Box 31, Folder 17)
        - Pulaski County (Box 31, Folder 18)
        - Rappahannock County (Box 31, Folder 19)
        - Richmond County (Box 31, Folder 20)
        - Roanoke County (Box 31, Folder 21)
        - Rockbridge County (Box 31, Folder 22)
        - Rockingham County (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Russell County (Box 32, Folder 2)
        - Scott County (Box 32, Folder 3)
        - Shenandoah County (Box 32, Folder 4)
        - Smyth County (Box 32, Folder 5)
        - Southampton County (Box 32, Folder 6)
        - Spotsylvania County (Box 32, Folder 7)
        - Stafford County (Box 32, Folder 8)
        - Surry County (Box 32, Folder 9)
        - Sussex County (Box 32, Folder 10)
        - Tazewell County (Box 32, Folder 11)